Okay, so we were discussing different issues
within Yayin Nesech, of course. We're going
to get into tonight more to some
examples of Mechallel Shabbat and things like
that, then we're going to talk about
what happens when the people touch the
bottle, open the bottle, shake the bottle,
corkscrew, all the different kind of things.
See how much we can get through.
Hopefully not too complicated tonight. So we
left, we left, last we left our
heroes. So in, yeah, okay, so there's
an interesting discussion they have here in
the notes, it's not in any of
the Marei Mekomot. What would be, yes
Donnie? How are you doing? I can't
see from your water. Refreshing. What was
that? I can't see from your water.
I got it. Could you clink glasses
with somebody who is has non, you
know, with a Jew, would that forbid
the wine in your cup? Okay, so
what do you think? No. Great, okay,
let's move on. So if you go
to source 29, Rav Moshe Feinstein. So
Rav Moshe is dealing with a She'ilah,
are you allowed to gift a bottle
of wine to a non-religious Jew, Mechallel
Shabbat b'Farhesia, if you know that, you
know, he's going to drink that wine?
Potentially you're selling him, if you sell
him non-Mevushal wine, it might be a
problem. So Rav Moshe in source 29
says yes. Rav Moshe says it's allowed,
right? If you look in source 29,
Rav Moshe, לכן כיון שאין איסור זה
מבורר. He explains already the whole thing
is already a little bit unclear. ויותר
נראה שלא נאסר מדין אלא מן המנהג.
This thing is more of a Minhag.
והלא נהגו להחמיר שלא ליתן יין למחלל
שבת עצמו. So we are not going
to go as far as to say
you can't gift it to him. Already
this whole idea we don't know how
to define Mechallel Shabbat, so it would
be fine if you'd like to give
your Mechallel Shabbat neighbor a, you know,
bottle of non-Mevushal wine. Rav Sternbuch in
source 30 as well, Rav Moshe Sternbuch
writes that the whole Gezeira, he says,
the whole Gezeira to treat the wine
of non-religious Jews as Stam Yeinam, that
actually was enacted for religious Jews to
prevent them from being negatively influenced by
the non-religious. But to just give it
to them that they can drink it,
that wouldn't be as, מכל מקום לא
שייך לאסור משום בנותיהם רק לדידם ולעצמם
לא שייך לאסור עליהם משום בנותיהם. It's
fine. The whole point if you is
to if you want to give them
the wine for them to drink, go
for it. So if that is your
in your liking, you can go ahead,
both according to Rav Moshe Feinstein, both
according to Rav Sternbuch, you can gift
that bottle of non-Mevushal wine. Is Rav
Sternbuch saying that when the non-religious person
drinks his own wine, correct, he's over
an Issur at all? No, no, he
might be over an Issur. But the
non-religious Jews were never prohibited from drinking
their own wine. So for me to
give him a bottle of wine, that's
not the Gezeira of Yayin Nesech. Okay,
there is an interesting... wait if you
say if you say there's a possible
problem with someone's Mechallel Shabbat, why would
it be permissible to give wine to
a person who was not Jewish at
all? He's not Jewish. So you'd be
giving him a bottle of wine, I
don't know. So he's going to drink
Treif wine? Right, he can have Treif
wine. Because because a Jew is going
to be drinking... Okay, I don't know.
No, I'm saying the where we're worried
about Stam Yeinam, Yayin Nesech, it doesn't
apply to a non-Jew. There were there
are other issues in gifting non-Jewish things
in terms of before Yom Tov and
things like that, but I don't know
this to be such an issue. Okay,
the next the next topic, the next
example is an interesting example and that
would be: could a Rav, could a
Mesader Kiddushin at the end of the
Sheva Brachot? So what happens is that
the moment that the Rav makes the
Bracha and he gives the Chatan to
drink, if that Chatan is a Mechallel
Shabbat, could you give him that wine
to drink? I don't know why we
had to go this, so again Rav
Moshe would say yes, Rav Sternbuch would
say yes. If you look actually at
source 31 in Rav Ovadia, he says
there's two more reasons to Meikel on
such a situation. One, we mentioned earlier,
why would we be Meikel on this
situation at a wedding of a non-religious
person being officiated by an Orthodox rabbi?
Kevod Habriyot. Kevod Habriyot. More than that.
What what what there's a good Chazara
for the Bechina. What was the Binyan
Tziyon or Rav Yaakov Ettlinger, the Aruch
LaNer's reason... In the shaila that he
was asked that a mechallel Shabbos who's
coming to shul is not considered—forget the
tinok shenishba. But the guy who's coming
to shul and then he's driving, how
could you call a guy mechallel Shabbos
b'farhesia? What's he doing? He's coming to
shul. So here's a guy, he asked
the rabbi to mesader kiddushin. Granted he's
not the frummest person in the world.
Okay. But he's a frum person. So
says Rav Ovadia, he has two reasons.
So number one he says, מכאן סמך
למה שנהגו כמה רבנים מישראל לשתות מכוס
של ברכת אירוסין ומכוס של שבע ברכות.
I was once giving a farher to
a kid. The kid was transferring from
a different school and he had learned
Kesuvos. So we—it was gemara with somewhere
in the first perek of Kesuvos he's
talking about the erusin and mishenasat. And
so I said let's stop for a
second, like how many parts to a
wedding are there? Right? So if you've
learned Kesuvos for an entire year you
should say two: erusin and nissuinn. He
says I think there's four. I go,
you're in! We got you. Okay? So
there's what doesn't matter which part, erusin
nissuinn, either part of the wedding or
sheva brachos, could he give it to
a mechallel Shabbos b'farhesia? Why? מיד שנגע
בו נתנסך נמצא דסבר ליה איסורא. You're
sort of like adding on to this
issur. ואף על פי שבשעת המסירה עדיין
הוא כשר. Okay, so he goes through
this whole thing. He says on the
underline—above it. והכי מצטרף ספקות אחריני. There's
this other reason to be meikel. But
he says, דהיינו שמתפלל ומקדש בשבת וגם
אינו מחלל שבת עם אדם גדול. Number
one, maybe he wouldn't—he's not like such
a, you know, a flamboyant mechallel Shabbos.
וגם אינו עובד בקרקע אפשר להקל. Okay?
Second of all, he says, ואולי יש
לומר דשאני חתן שמכפר לו עוונותיו. He
said on the under the chuppah. So
what? It's very cute. Okay? This—this is
the reason I mentioned before, this is
the reason this is why there's a—there's
a minhag you probably never been to
a wedding during Aseres Yemei Teshuva. You
think back to your times of going
to weddings you probably never been to
a wedding Aseres Yemei Teshuva. Why? Because
the suggestion is when you get married
it's mitchaper avonos. We don't like to
do things that are quick fixes. That's
why we don't wait for Kiddush Levana
not only for to chapper a mitzvah
right after Yom Kippur because it's—it's machnis
the Shechina, I—I should bring it on
my own. So that's one of the
reasons you don't weddings. So there's a
teshuva of Rav Dovid Tzvi Hoffmann who's
the Melamed L'hoil and he—from Germany—and he
says I searched a reason for this
and I could not find one person
who said it was assur and punkt
I got married in Aseres Yemei Teshuva
and I'm doing okay. So anyway, but
that's the—that's Rav Ovadia. Fine. Okay. So
the next few questions. So we saw
that in—we saw if you go to
the Shulchan Aruch for a second, we
saw in seif yud-ches. Okay, we saw
in seif yud-ches that a goy—that the
Shulchan Aruch says that if a non-Jew
lifts the bottle of the wine, higbiyo
veyatzak hayayin, that's assur. But higbiya velo
she-, he picks it up and he
doesn't shake it and he doesn't touch
it, it's mutter. Okay? That's one. You
saw in yud-zayin, right, if you go
one back, that shaking the bottle, right,
just shaking it without lifting the bottle,
right, that would be assur and the
Rema would be mutter if it was
a makom hefsed. So the shaila is
if a non-Jew opens your bottle of
wine, we're going to get to all
these examples soon, he opens it, he
doesn't shake it, he doesn't lift it,
he's very, very—you know, he's got one
of those fancy, you know, things and
he doesn't do anything at all, it
seems that we should be pretty lenient
about it. If he shakes it, the
Shulchan Aruch would be—would be assur, the
Rema would be meikel potentially, but it
seemed that we would be meikel about
it. Okay. Next. What happens if a
goy touches your wine by accident? Okay,
by accident. So if the—the non-Jewish waiter
comes out, he sees the wine that's
on your table and he by accident
puts his finger in your wine. Now,
the first thing you should be saying
is, why would I want to drink
my wine anymore? That's disgusting. No, you
just said already you need intent to—so
now if the waiter is a Muslim,
okay, what—what would we say? We would
say it's fine. Right? It's gross but
it's fine. We would even say that
according to many of the poskim, not
only is it fine, it's fine to
do what? Fine to even drink it.
Okay? If the waiter is Christian, okay,
then the Shulchan Aruch would say it's
assur and the Rema might even allow
it. Says the Chochmas Adam in source
32. So the Chochmas Adam writes that
you could rely on this leniency potentially.
He says, וכן באקום שלנו מותר אפילו
בשתייה, that even this accidental because that's
what we said before there wasn't intent.
דלעולם נחזינהו חד דרגא, we dump it
down one level. ומכל מקום אין להתיר
רק דווקא במקום הפסד. unless like we
saw earlier in the Rama, and then
he adds also ואין לפרסם הדבר בפני
עם הארץ. We also don't want people
knowing about it. Okay, fine. Next next
topic is an interesting topic. There's not
a lot of notes in it, and
that would be what about getting wine
on an El Al flight? Okay, El
Al has both I mean probably not
where I sit, but maybe where other
people sit, there's wine that they serve.
And they serve mevushal wine and they
also serve non-mevushal wine. Okay? So this
is a big question. This is a
big question. So there are what what
would be the reasons to be machmir
and to not get non-mevushal wine on
an El Al flight? Let's go. They
quote in the notes at least four
reasons that they want to discuss being
meikel. Why? No one's supervising them. Okay,
so no one's supervising it. Fine. Next.
Well potentially it hits all the things.
They pick it up, they may not
be shomer Shabbos. Right, first of all
we saw before from Rav Shlomo Zalman
that we are machmir about amei ha'aretz
or mechallel Shabbos, you know, unless there's
real great need. We only are meikel
when we said what might happen, as
we heard before, maybe there's embarrassment. There's
no embarrassment here. Okay? Or I don't
need the wine from you. I just
don't have to drink the wine. What
else we discuss last week? They pour
it into the non-Jewish passenger's cup. Correct,
the whole bottle might be assur. Right?
Depends on where it came from. Okay.
So then there are a few reasons
to be meikel. What are the reasons
to be meikel? Come on. So we
always want to be meikel. First of
all, we don't know how to define
mechallel Shabbos. That's number one. Second, even
if we knew what it meant. Exactly.
Okay, what did the flight attendant do
with the wine? They didn't touch it.
What did they do? They poured it.
So like the Rama said, we might
be meikel on that. If you look
at source 33 in the Binat Daat,
says the following. In terms of the
issue of leaving things unattended, מותר להשאיר
חילוני עם בקבוק יין פתוח. You can
leave the wine with him, ואם היין
מונח על השולחן ומיועד לשתיה, ein lehashiro
lechatchila, you know, it's not lechatchila but
אבל אם השאירו נראה שלא נאסר היין
בפרט במקום הפסד. Meaning we would be
lenient although you should generally not leave
open non-mevushal wine with your local non-you
know, your local non-religious Jew. Nonetheless, we're
we're, you know, if you see that
maybe something happened, וניכר שרק החזיר יין
למקומו ולא שתה. Okay, only if I'm
really sure that he didn't touch it.
He says in the footnote the following.
נראה שבימינו אין לחוש כלל לנגיעה בתוך
הבקבוק. No one's touching the wine inside.
Okay? The reason the Rama said beforehand
was because maybe they're going to, no
one's touching the wine. וכן נראה דאין
לחוש שמא שתה ישירות מפי הבקבוק שאין
דרכו. Not drinking out of the bottle.
So really potentially we could be meikel.
So if you want to send out
the notes, you'll see that Rav Goldvicht
junior, well I don't know, there's many
juniors, but Rav Ariel Yehuda says that
he talked to Rav Danino, who's the
Rav of El Al. He says we
do serve non-mevushal wine. It comes with
special like a note that says some
of the reasons that they're meikel. You
can ask for a closed bottle, but
really it's best it would not be
ideal. You'd be relying on a number
of kulos for if you really needed
that non-mevushal bottle of wine on that
El Al flight. It would be better
to avoid that shaila. What if they
give you a can of kosher wine,
you know, like some of the Rashi
makes cans of wine and they give
it to you closed? So if they
gave it to you closed, first of
all if it was closed, we're going
to talk about closed in a second,
how sealed it have to be. But
let's assume it's sealed properly and it's
one of the things and potentially you
picked it off, then for sure it
would be fine. For sure it would
be fine. I can't is there a
lot of canned non-mevushal wine out there?
I have no idea. I can't imagine.
This is mamash tarti de-satri. Rabbi, there
are small bottles. Small bottles. Small bottles.
Individual bottles. Right. Okay. Okay fine. So
this does lead into the next topic
of this does this leads into the
next discussion which is very similar and
that is are you allowed if you're
at a restaurant, which the more the
case would be in Eretz Yisrael but
ordering at a kosher restaurant obviously and
there is a non- not like the
guy who was attacked at Burger King
with his Magen David. We're not talking
about that guy. That guy. We're not
safe anywhere. We're not safe anywhere. A
Jew can't even go to a Burger
King. Anyway, the this The shayla is
what's going to happen if there is
there you know the non-Jewish waiter or
the non you know is going to
if he's a if he's the you
know potentially Christian or Muslim and is
going to open it. So we said
you know if there's a concern you
know there's not an embarrassment piece here
because like you're the one asking for
the wine. If he can open the
wine without moving it if it's you
know we're pretty lenient about it but
you will find certain restaurants on a
certain hashgacha if it's not mevushal wine
that it's going to be poured by
what appears to be a frum religious
looking Jew. Okay source 34. What happens
if a person has non-religious parents? So
you're at your non-religious parents non-religious family
members and they pour the wine. So
what based on what we've said? It's
embarrassment right? It's embarrassment. So we look
in source 34. So Ashkenazi for sure.
The Sfardim even say the following. Isn't
there also the inyan of Kibbud Av
V'eim there which which if if there's
some to be meikel on you might
say that the Kibbud Av V'eim if
there's a not for something else? Do
I need to call Art? What's going
on here? How is this happening a
lot? I'm not saying drink the wine.
So yes and no. The Rashi quotes
at the beginning of Emor from the
Gemara in Shas that when the when
your parent say violate a mitzvah you
don't violate the mitzvah. But I'm just
saying if you've got multiple inyanim and
the Rama says okay so that's what
I'm saying so you have to right
right right but it would depend if
your parents are let's say a real
flamboyant mechallel Shabbos okay correct correct. So
the Ashkenazi for sure meikel. The Sfardim
in source 34 say the following. He
explains just says Rav Yitzchak Yosef שמקום
צרה גדול יש מקום לסמוך על היתר
זה ולמנוע מצוה מריבה וגדול השלום that
yes family harmony is going to be
more important. לכתחילה יש לחוש לדעת המחמיר
we should be machmir but I understand
that a person would be able to
be meikel in such a situation. Wasn't
there a discussion in the poskim whether
they were even gozer in that scenario?
No no no for your parent no
but if they're only difference between treating
non-religious Jews as mechallel Shabbos as opposed
to non-Jews. No I think there is
a klal of stam yeinam yaynasach. There's
reasons to be meikel on it so
what do you mean? Meikel on embarrassment
but I don't think they were not
gozer in a situation like this. We
only extend the non-religious because you're concerned
of some sort of influence right? Yeah
but then becomes very vague. Influence by
parents is never influence. Of what? Like
they're already what they are. I guess...
No but if they're non-religious they're non-religious.
Right but I'm saying why enough to
worry about being their kids? Correct correct
but there's still a gzira that's in
place. Correct I would think so I
would think so. Okay next what is
the halacha if these parents make the
same thing same situation but they make
Kiddush? So one more piece and then
we'll go to the next topic. So
if you look in source 35 go
to the Darchei Teshuva okay? So a
non-religious person makes Kiddush drinks from the
cup and then he starts pouring for
everybody else. So now what do you
do? So now obviously you could refuse
the wine you don't have to drink
wine. Okay but let's assume you've already
yotzei with this Kiddush. What? You're still
yotzei with this Kiddush? You're yotzei with
this Kiddush. With a mechallel Shabbos? Yeah.
Yeah. Is he in the category of
mechallel Shabbos who made Kiddush? Right well
that I'm saying that's one is the
Binyan Tzion's psak if he's making Kiddush
he's not that meaning again like I
said a few weeks ago we're all
mechallel Shabbos in some regard so if
it's a real I shouldn't say that.
Some of us more than correct that's
what I should have said. So a
person who is mechallel Shabbos can motzi
you and a mitzvah he might not
be the person you want being the
shliach tzibbur blowing the shofar things like
that. There are unless a person is
a real mumar. If a person is
a mumar lehachis they can't count in
your minyan. Right person is a mumar
lehachis they can't count as your 10th
person in a minyan. Okay so the
Darchei Teshuva says the following. Again one
reason that it would be okay to
drink is like Rav Moshe. Who really
knows what this means mechallel Shabbos b'farhesia?
We don't know what this means. That's
reason number one. Then says the Darchei
Teshuva quoted the Knesses Yechezkel and a
few others he says I know it's
a little hard to see but he
says it in a situation of a
loss if a non-Jew does not do
nisuch he's not a libations kind of
guy and he touched it that really
wouldn't be asur. So it really would
be okay if the person who you
know who would be there would be
reason to be meikel. It would be
better not to drink that wine but
if you had to. or whatever, you're
worried about embarrassment, there would be enough
to suggest that we could be meikil.
But I thought we said today there
is no such thing really as the
libation in the avodah zarah in the
same way, so correct, so most of
the, so there's probably a lot of
room to be meikil in that situation.
Okay. Okay fine. Yeah they mentioned something
interesting. At the end of all weddings,
so the waiters go around, let's assume
again you've got a Muslim or Christian
waiter they're grabbing all the bottles. So
now what? So what happens to all
the wine that's left in those bottles?
So again if the bottle's going to
be closed, so that's not going to
be a problem. If they're not really
shaking it, that's also not going to
be a problem. And maybe they're not
really touching the wine directly, so again
we would probably be meikil in some
of these situations. Okay. Okay fine. Let's
go to source thirty-seven. So... Oh no
we have a little bit of time.
Okay fine. Sorry. My notes are off.
Okay. Go to Kuf Chaf Vav, a
little Shulchan Aruch here. We're going to
skip a little bit to Kuf Chaf
Vav before we go back to the
book. Go to Kuf Chaf Vav, קכ\"ו
א. Okay. So let's review for a
second the following. So look at קכ\"ו
א. So we learned earlier if you
want to note, source nineteen was the
Gemara in Avodah Zarah that when wine
is poured in a continuous stream that
concept is called nitzok, right? And that
if I pour that from the bottle
to something else that connects the two
and they're both considered assur. Okay says
the Shulchan Aruch the following. קכ\"ו א
המערה יין לתוך כלי שיש בו יין
עובדי כוכבים האסור בהנאה נאסר כל היין
שבכלי. If I'm pouring something into a
kli and that vessel, that kli has
assur wine in it, then I assur-ed
everything in the kli ha'elyon she'amar hanitzok
because whatever's on top is מחבר בין
היין שבכלי העליון ובין היין שבכלי התחתון,
everything like Rashi held earlier, it's all
connected. Right? The stam yeinam is connected
to everything else and therefore all the
wine is assur. ורואים כאילו יין של
איסור מעורב בשל היתר, I view it
as if everything gets mixed. Ve'im ira
bekituh but if I did it drip
drip, then it would be potentially a
little bit different. Beis. Says the Shulchan
Aruch, however, נצוק חיבור הני מילי בהפסד
מועט. That's only potentially if it's but
אבל בהפסד מרובה כגון שהוציא מחבית לכלי
שיש בו יין נסך מותר, we could
rely on Rabbeinu Tam who held earlier
that nitzok is not such an issue
here. Rashi held it is, Rabbeinu Tam
holds it's not. So you could rely
on that if you need. What is
a great loss? So says the Rama,
ואין חילוק בין אם היה הרבה יין
בחבית או לא אפילו יכול למכור לעובדי
כוכבים וכל מה שבקנקן או בכוס מקרי
הפסד מועט. So see that again. The
Rama's defining a small loss, mah shebakankan
anyone that's left in the remaining cup
or bottle and the wine that's left
in the barrel, that's considered hefsed merubeh.
Okay. Ve'davka beya'in nesech fine. Okay, now.
Hold on and go to the Shach
in sif katan tes, I believe. Yes.
Okay. The Shach in sif katan tes
says that this whole kula the Rama
benefits this whole thing the Rama said
last time. Ah we're meikil all these
different kind of thing. Says the Shach,
it's not true when it comes to
this concept. So the Shach writes the
following. He says... let's go down like
two lines. ונראה דאף על גב דהמנהג
בסתם יינם בזמן הזה. Even though you're
right there says the Rama that all
the wine that's in today are mutar
behana'ah, מכל מקום אמרינן בזה נצוק חיבור.
I know, I know says the Shach
that you Rama said there's no libations
and there's no such thing anymore, but
if the wine is poured into a
cup, nitzok still applies. וכיון דמדין אסור
בהנאה ופשוט הוא. So the Shach says
although nitzok only applies when the wine
is being poured is for... forbidden, meaning
if I took pig juice and I
poured pig juice into my cereal bowl,
there's nitzuk and it's all assur. Or
the other way around: I had milk
and I have pig juice, it's all
khibor. But you should be asking like
the Shakh says, that doesn't matter anymore,
why? Because you Rama said it doesn't
apply anymore. Says the Shakh that's not
what the Rama said. Since the wine
in the cup would have really been
entirely forbidden had it been touched by
a guy who does nessakh. You're right,
you're right, it doesn't apply anymore, but
that's just in practice. In theory, there
is a halakha of yayin nessakh. And
if we found a guy and that
guy... if a guy came in right
now and he says, \"I love avoda
zara\" and \"I pour wine all the
time,\" and he took all the wine
in this shul and touched it, that
wine would be one thousand percent yayin
nessakh. It would treif up every every
inch that he touched it with. And
the Rama would not be meikel. Why?
Because the guy worships avoda zara. So
therefore, says the Shakh, because the wine
could have been assur, because he could
have touched it, nitzuk still applies. So
therefore, says the Shakh, that is how
I hold, and therefore even though the
Rama agrees that if a non-Jew left
his wine in the glass and you'd
like poured a little bit in, it
becomes forbidden. Nonetheless, says the Shakh, we
hold of this concept of nitzuk even
according to the Rama. Now, before we
continue, let's just finish this. Now go
to hey. If you go to seif
hey. Go to seif hey. Says the
Shulkhan Arukh: המערה יין לתוך כלי עובד
כוכבים. So says the Rama, if you...
says the Shulkhan Arukh, if you are
pouring nitzuk does not apply שלא הודח
ואין משקה בטופח על השאר אסור בשתייה.
The nitzuk does not apply if what
you're pouring into is not washed. And
it's also gross. Muttar afilu bishtiya. But
he says nitzuk not apply if the
cup to which you are pouring into,
the little thing that I'm holding, was
not washed, but the remaining wine has
dried up to the point that it's
going to like leave your hands wet.
Basically the Rama clarifies and he says:
אם יש בו כדי להטפיח אוסר בניצוק.
That if the remaining... the wine that's
remaining in the non-Jew's cup is still
moist to wet your hands, then nitzuk
would apply. If it's very very dry,
then maybe nitzuk doesn't apply. And then
the Rama adds one more thing: מיהו
אינו אוסר יותר מאילו מעורב בו ואם
סתם יינם בטל בששים. That what could
I also have here? Bitul beshishim. So
what would that mean? If you had
a little bit of the wine left
and it was still moist but you
put in... but the barrel that I'm
pouring from is massive, so you would
have bitul beshishim. Okay. So they give
a few examples about this. Does bitul
beshishim mean min be-mino? He's saying bitul...
yeah, like we saw earlier from the...
when it comes to yayin nessakh. Even
min be-mino? Correct. Min be-mino we would
be... that was the whole Sherry cask
shayla. Yeah, yeah. Yeah. And you would
say you would prefer the nitzuk concept?
Yeah. The nitzuk, yeah. במין שבמינו ובשאין
מינו is be-shishim, right? Correct. Correct. Okay,
there's a whole thing in the notes
here, you can read about the Jerusalem
Wine Festival, if you've ever been. Okay?
So it's your problem. But, you know,
could you attend the... this wine festival
if you like. But go to the
back of the booklet now for a
second. Okay. So one more... one more
piece here before we get to the
next topic of how sealed something has
to be. Says the Darkhei Teshuva in
source 36. There's some a bunch of
things in the notes that I'm skipping
just because I skip the things that
are not as in the material. Says
the Darkhei Teshuva, again it's a little
hard to see, but what happens if
a... שניצוק יש בו יין מבושל אסור
משום ניצוק חיבור. ובשאר דעת הפוסקים שהשך
לא נתבאר לו דעתם מזה להדיא להכא
נראה דודאי המערה יין מבושל כשר לסתם
יינם. If mevushal wine, okay, your regular
Moscato is poured into the cup of
a non-mevushal wine that's being drunk by
a non-Jew, יש לנהוג איסור מהשניצוק והכלי
העליון מן המבושל. It'll be a problem
that that it would potentially... that even
if a Jew pours mevushal wine, right?
Pours mevushal wine into the cup of
non-mevushal wine, the mevushal wine in the
bottle would be assur because of nitzuk.
Okay, so hope this doesn't happen to
you too much. Why not? Non-mevushal wine
that was touched by what? So he
says the following. He says that the
whole point is because you view it
as the last line he says: יש
לנהוג איסור מהשניצוק והכלי העליון מן המבושל.
We view the forbidden... Correct, correct, correct,
correct. Okay. Isn't that the Shakh's explanation
also of the Rama that if you
have treif in the bottle, you'd be
fine? Right. Notwithstanding the fact that it
tastes like treif. Right. Correct. But it
would be a problem. Okay. Next. A
non-Jewish guest in your house. We've done
this a few times already, so if
the non-guest is a Muslim, non-religious, if
it's a Christian. Okay. What about pouring
things in your sink? What happens? So
if you go to dalet in kuf-chaf-vav,
so you there your non-Jewish cleaning lady
is taking that bottle of wine and
she's pouring it in the sink. Let's,
before we talk about if the sink
is treifed up, says the Shulchan Aruch
in sif dalet: עובד כוכבים המערה יין
מכלי לאשפה או למקום לכלוך אין דרך
ניסוך בכך. So let's say you have
a very very fancy bottle of wine
and you left that bottle of wine
out and your non-Jewish cleaning lady, because
all they know is move things around
and then, you know, stack, so they
decide, you know what, I'm going to
get rid of this bottle of wine,
and they pour it out, and you
run over, and you take that bottle
out of her hand, or maybe his
hand, I don't know, it's 2026. What,
what's the status of the wine left
in the bottle? Can you drink that
wine now? They poured it, they touched
it, not the wine. Cleaning lady may
not know it's wine. Okay. Let's assume
they know it's wine. They're pouring it.
So says the Shulchan Aruch, yeah, but
the Gemara had talked about if the
goy is pouring into cement, to the
garbage: הכל מותר בין מה שהוציא לחוץ
ובין מה שבפנים. Why? Why? That's not
avodah zarah. You're clearly not doing it
for libation purposes if the place that
you are dumping it into is the
garbage. So if they're dumping it into
the sink and you stop with them,
the remaining wine would be allowed simply
because they weren't doing things for avodah
zarah purposes. And the Shakh in zayin
says not only that, in this situation,
he says: כתב הש\"ך דאפילו נגע עובד
כוכבים שעה שמערה הכל מותר. Why? b'atzmo
shovei l'ibud. They're just spilling it out.
הרי בטלה מחשבתו ושוי כמיא בעלמא. They
view it as water. They know it's
wine. They have all the intentions. They
know it's wine. They're pouring it out.
But they're doing it to be garbage.
ואין כאן מחשבת ניסוך כלל. It's a
very important line of the Shakh: machsheves
nisuch, like melaches machsheves on Shabbos. There
has to be a thought process to
it. If my thought process here is
that I'm throwing in the garbage, that's
not nisuch, that's not yayin nesech, and
therefore everything would be okay. If you
go one more, and if you go
to kuf-chaf-dalet, you go back, kuf-chaf-dalet, chaf-zayin.
What happens if the non-Jew... there is
a siman here where they did it
to be angry at you. Oh, yeah.
Oh, yeah. Look at the last Rama,
kuf-chaf-dalet: עובד כוכבים שנגע ביינו של ישראל
להכעיס כדי לאסרו עליו. Like, look at
what I did to your wine, I
assered it. Ha ha. אפילו אינם יודעים
אלא באומדנות המוכיחות. He says, says the
Rama, that non-Jew deliberately touches your wine,
he wants to like mess with you,
he wants to asser your wine. So
says the Rama, the wine's still permitted.
Why? Because he really why does he
want to do, he just wants you
to dispose of the wine. So he's
also viewing it as nothing. So it
wouldn't really be such a problem. Unless
he's doing libation? That would be a
problem. That would be a problem. So
I tell you something, if you look
in the Taz, if you look in
the Taz, it's a Taz in lamed-vav.
So the Taz says that there was
a maiseh like this: כמו מעשה בתרומת
הדשן. says, ah, I have a story
of the Trumas Hadeshen. Okay, Trumas Hadeshen
lived, you know, 200 years earlier, yeah.
150 years earlier. שהיה עובד כוכבים לפני
הגיגית, so there were some like people
that were there: v'lachshu zeh lazeh, they
were whispering: ואחר כך טבל אחד אצבעו
בתירוש, he sticks his finger in the
wine: u'matzatz mimeno b'piv, and then he
spits it out, and then... ושחקו למו
פיהם מלוא שחוק ורצו יהודים אחריהם ואמרו
להם קלקלתם יין שלנו. So the Jews
chased them and they caught up to
them and the Jews asked them why'd
you ruin our wine? שבו לא ידעו
שהוא אסור בשביל זה. We didn't know
that it would forbid it. והרגישו יהודים
מתוך הלחש שכוונתם היה לנסך לקלקל. Meaning
they see these goyim doing things they
dip their put their fingers in they
spit it out whatever and then they
run away and the Jews chase after
them. They say what did you do?
We didn't know we would assur it.
So the Taz so the Trumat HaDeshen
says really you should say it's fine.
But the fact they were whispering is
like I think they know what they're
doing and you know he assur’d it.
Okay good. Okay let's start the next
topic. Let's go to the Gemara the
final like big Gemara every topic starts
with a Gemara there's one a little
bit later but okay. So the very
very important topic of leaving wine unattended.
Okay I have a bottle of wine
what does it mean that I could
leave it with a goy without a
goy maids workers things like that. Says
the Gemara. מיחדים אצלו יין says the
Gemara in Avoda Zara I can but
with the Ger Toshav we're talking about
מיחדים אצלו יין ומפקדין אצלו יין. I
could leave wine you know unattended in
his store let's say for a short
period of time that's meyachdin. אבל אין
מפקדין אצלו יין. What's mafkidim? Like watch
like פרק המפקיד בבבא מציעא you watch
it for me. Okay so the Gemara
is very clear that I can't like
deposit my wine with you. I could
leave it with you you could watch
it for a few minutes but I'm
not like leaving it for you. Rashi
right here so Rashi says the following
that he says ישראל מניח בחנותו של
עכו״ם כדי מיל ויותר we'll come back
to this in a second. Let's say
he's got a non-Jewish worker and the
guy says or I'm sorry Ger Toshav
and he says hey I gotta run
out for a minute I gotta do
an errand. So as long as he's
going let's say a mil or more
מה שאין כן עובדי כוכבים. That's only
true when it comes to a Ger
Toshav but a goy כיון דלא פלח
לא נגע ולא מנסך that he might
not he's not going to do anything
ולמגע עובדי כוכבים דאתו מעלמא בביתיה לא
חיישינן. We're also not worried that maybe
he might come and switch wine from
his own house כי אם דלהנהו בכך
אינו מניחו ליגע וחלופי בזמן מועט לית
לן למיחש. I'm also not worried that
what man he might do he might
switch it out. So Rashi explains either
I'm worried with a goy that a
goy is going to touch the wine
that I'm leaving with him or he
might unintentionally do what with it? Run
home I'll get my bottle of wine
I'll switch it and he's never going
to know he's never going to know.
Okay? The Ger Toshav we're going to
be more lenient for. Okay so meaning
wine that's left unattended with the Ger
Toshav becomes forbidden immediately if with an
Oveid Kochavim even with a Ger Toshav
if it's longer depends how long it's
going to be and wine that's in
his home wine left unattended with a
goy in your home that was a
weird thing but in my home is
going to be a problem. Meaning in
a Ger Toshav's home I can leave
it with him for a little bit
for sure not with a goy. In
my house a goy I can't even
leave for a short amount of time.
Okay says the Shulchan Aruch קכ״ח א׳.
Now this will get into the topic
of what is considered leaving how long
can it be sealed things like that.
Says the Shulchan Aruch in Sif Katan
Aleph. עובדי כוכבים שנתייחד עם היין a
goy that is hanging out with your
wine afilu b’rshuso even in your house
afilu sha’a achas even for a minute
assur b’hana’ah. אבל מי שנודע לנו but
if we know she’eino oveid kochavim he's
not an idol worshipper מותר לייחד יין
אצלו בביתו we can leave it in
your house l’zman mu’at only for a
short amount of time to go at
least a mil or yoter אפילו בבית
שכולו עובדי כוכבים. Okay that's the Shulchan
Aruch that if an idol worshipping non-Jew
is left with some wine assur. Okay
if you know this guy bows down
to Buddha and you said can you
watch my bottle of Moscato while it's
open straight up bad idea. Okay what
now again what would be the case
with your Muslim friends? It would seemingly
be fine it would seemingly be fine.
Then the Rama adds עובד כוכבים שבחוץ
לארץ he doesn't necessarily mean like he
he just means our goyim אף על
פי שאינו עובד כוכבים מכל מקום אין
מיחדים אצלם that even though we're not
so concerned with our non-Jews it still
forbids the wine. Says the Shach in
Sif Katan Dalet. So it's a big
Shach. The first thing he quotes is
this Rashba. This Rashba we've seen before;
it's a very important Rashba that all
Christians are idol worshippers and therefore it
doesn't matter, but even though the Rema
some would be lenient for a Christian
today, so he says, quotes the Rashba.
If you look about seven eight lines
down he says אבל לדידן דשרינן מגע
ובסתם ייננו we're more lenient with these
things, but nonetheless he says l'chatchila mias
asser. Okay? So there even though the
Rema would be meikel, we are machmir.
If you leave a non-Jewish person with
your wine, potentially could asser that wine.
Okay. If you go back to the
Shach in the sif katan alef of
the Shach, so the Shach here says
that whenever there is reason of concern
that a non-Jewish cleaning would touch the
wine, that is going to be a
problem and he writes in the last
line, first he says ino oveid kochavim
like a ger toshav or Yishmaelim, that's
the Shach, a Muslim is not a
goy, but he writes in the last
line אף על גב דעובדי כוכבים בזמן
הזה לאו עובדי כוכבים נינהו אסור היכא
דאיכא למיחש שנגע משום הנאתו. Even if
that Muslim in your house, he's not
worshipping anything with it, but he likes
how it feels on his hands, he
likes how it tastes, he likes how
he smells it in the glass when
he swirls it around, if he's doing
it for his benefit it's going to
be a problem. So therefore really unattended
wine is going to be an issue.
So again according to the Shulchan Aruch,
unattended wine with a Christian or idol
worshipper even a few seconds going to
be a problem. The Rema would be
lenient but we're still machmir about it
and wine left even for with a
Muslim potentially up to a mil would
be okay. Now everybody's going to say
it doesn't matter, I double sealed it.
So now let's look at this idea
of what does it mean to double
seal something. Okay. Now go a little
bit further to Shulchan Aruch Kuf Lamed.
Kuf Lamed Aleph. It's a big whatever
we'll look at it outside. In Kuf
Lamed Aleph based on a Gemara in
Avodah Zarah that you can send wine
to a non-Jew with a non-Jew I'm
sorry if it has says the Shulchan
Aruch מותר להפקיד ולשלוח יין ביד עובדי
כוכבים אם הוא חתום בחותם בתוך חותם
so that's a double seal. Or a
like a lock. Like a seal and
a lock. Something that I have where
else do we have this? We have
this earlier in also in halacha. Where
else do we have this? Don't say
microwave. Where else do we have this?
Where? With meat. Okay we know we
can do this. Okay. So what does
it mean a double seal? So now
go to daled in the Shulchan Aruch.
So says the Shulchan Aruch what does
it mean a double seal? So he
says כיצד הוא חותם בתוך חותם סותם
החבית בכלי שאינו מהודק כדרך שחותמין כל
אדם so again a very loose fitting
like it's a cap, that's just seal
number one. Okay? And then you cement
it or you really make sure that
it's firm and you can't open it,
that would be a second seal. Okay?
And he says in the last thing
וכן כל שינוי שמשנה בדברים שאין דרך
כל אדם כחותם אחד וטיחה וקשירה חותם
שני. So long as I did it
in an unusual way and I did
something that's really I could double seal
it. Okay? So now. Says Rav Moshe
Feinstein in source thirty-eight. So Rav Moshe
says what's the real goal of a
double seal? What's the real goal of
a double seal? So a double seal
is not only that it's just extra
it's just better protection. A double seal
means that I know there's no way
the goy could have done it. Like
we're talking in a second, even a
soda can, if that goy opens it
there's no way that he's going to
be able to do what? Close it
back up. Okay? Fine. So says Rav
Moshe in source thirty-eight. So Rav Moshe
writes ונראה דכל הנידון דאפשר לזייף. The
whole point is that I can't forge
it, I can't duplicate it. מפני הטורח
תולין שלא יזייף. It's a lot a
lot of work to do that. And
therefore says Rav Moshe that's what it
means a double seal. So he says
ובחותם אפילו אחד אם כזה שאי אפשר
לזייף. It doesn't have to mean davka
double seal. So long as the seal
that I put on, double seal in
halacha just means you can't forge it.
And you can't change it or put
something else or swipe it out or
do something. That doesn't davka mean a
double seal it could do anything. מותר
אף בוודאי כשכל עכו\"ם doesn't matter as
long as I could do something that
would take a lot of effort and
therefore so much effort that it's not
worth it, it's so much. one seal
would be good enough and that would
be okay. So what does that mean?
So if you look in Source 39,
the Steipler says that a cap that
has a safety ring. Okay, if you
let's say you bought that bottle Moscato,
okay, 'cause you're high end, okay? It
has a safety ring on it. So
is that a double seal or not?
So it does not seem to be
a double seal. It's one cap with
one ring. Why would it be okay?
'Cause you can't copy it. Once it
breaks, it breaks. Unless I gotta go
back to the factory and ask them
to do it again. By the way,
this is the famous debate in Hilchos
Shabbos. The debate in Hilchos Shabbos with
opening bottle caps. You know there are
plenty of poskim that say you can
open bottles on Shabbos. Some say you
can open cans on Shabbos. But those
poskim, some say you can't open cans
of issues on machoichech and tikkun kli
and like that. My Rebbe is machmir
on those things. As much as I
tried to get into a meikel, it
has not worked yet. I'm working on
that. When Rav Neuburger was by us
when he came in October, he was
by us for lunch. My wife says
to him, \"Rav Neuburger, rethought the, you
know, adjusting ovens on Yom Tov?\" He
goes, \"No, I still think it's ha'avara.\"
I'm like \"Oh. What about the warming
drawer on Shabbos?\" He goes \"No.\" I'm
like \"I gotta ask other people.\" So
on the shaila on Shabbos is that
for those that say you can't open
a bottle on Shabbos, it's because it's
tikkun mane. Not an issue of makeh
b'patish, which could potentially be, but I
create a kli. Before I open this
bottle, there was no bottle because it
was unusable and now it's an open
bottle. For example, you open a bag
of potato chips on Shabbos and now
Rav Moshe writes, so now it becomes
a storage container. That's why people when
they open a bag of something on
Shabbos, you should put into another bag
so that's your actual storage, not using
that. So Rav Vajeh writes in a
teshuva, depends on the soda bottle. Plastic
soda bottles, the way they make them
is that the ring is on the
bottle, the cap goes on top and
then it's merged together. That's not tikkun
mane, they were separate to begin with.
But if you ever had a metal
bottle, okay, so the metal ring, or
if you look on like Rashi, you
know like sparkling grape juice stuff like
that, that seal is not one, it's
not two seals made together, it's one
seal that they put on and then
they like melt it on top and
then you break it off. That's a
problem on Shabbos according to almost all
poskim because that I mammesh, it was
not usable beforehand and now I made
it usable. So if you look here
in Source 40, Source 39, we'll do
39 and 40, then we'll pick it
up next time with corks and things
like that. So first the Steipler writes
in Source 39 שמכסה הברגה בבקבוק יין
חותם בתוך חותם הכי טוב. So the
Steipler again says like exactly what we
said, a cap, even a screw-on cap,
but it's strong enough and I know
that that you can't replicate that, that
would again be considered a double seal.
And finally, the Mara D'Asra points out
the same thing we just said, that
the whole point is that it's a
torach rav vahotza'os. It's a lot of
work. If I'm gonna break this seal,
fill it up wine from somewhere else,
and somehow come back and re-put this
seal back, that is too much work
to do for an eight-dollar bottle of
Moscato wine. So therefore in these situations
where I'm not really so concerned, and
we're going to learn next week, this
might even be true if one seal
is a regular screw cap and the
other seal is just aluminum foil, right?
If you open a bottle of sparkling
Rashi grape juice, okay, so there is
that aluminum foil on the top of
it. So that's not a seal. Let
me tell you something. You take that
off, you ever try getting a sleeping
bag back into once you open it
up? Impossible. I don't know how many
times you go camping, Randy, it's impossible.
You know when the mattress comes, you
open it, you're not getting it back
in. So the poskim say, even the
foil, I'm gonna start like stretching it
back out. So even that, as long
as the thing that I'm having on
it will create enough tircha, then we
have room to be meikel that that
would be considered a double seal. Okay,
we will hold it here Im Yirtzeh
Hashem next time.